<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The famous bull in Cœna Domini published at Rome every Maunday Thursday against hereticks and all infringers of ecclesiastical liberties with a preface containing some reflections on the bull, and animadversions on the late account of the proceedings of the Parliament of Paris.</title>
            <title>Pastoralis Romani Pontificis vigilantia. English &amp; Latin</title>
            <author>Catholic Church. Pope (1605-1621 : Paul V)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12412114</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12412114</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61558</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61558)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 276:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The famous bull in Cœna Domini published at Rome every Maunday Thursday against hereticks and all infringers of ecclesiastical liberties with a preface containing some reflections on the bull, and animadversions on the late account of the proceedings of the Parliament of Paris.</title>
                  <title>Pastoralis Romani Pontificis vigilantia. English &amp; Latin</title>
                  <author>Catholic Church. Pope (1605-1621 : Paul V)</author>
                  <author>Paul V, Pope, 1552-1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Parallel English and Latin texts.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Papal documents.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>France. --  Parlement (Paris)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61558:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61558:1"/>
            <p>The Famous Bull <hi>IN CAENA DOMINI,</hi> Publiſhed at <hi>ROME</hi> every <hi>Maunday Thurſday</hi> againſt Hereticks, and all Infringers of Eccleſiaſtical Liberties.</p>
            <p>With a PREFACE containing ſome Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the Bull, and Animadverſions on the late Account of the Proceedings of the PARLIAMENT of <hi>PARIS.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the Year. 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:61558:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61558:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AFTER ſo many and ſo loud Out-cries againſt that juſt and neceſſary diſtinction of <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Popery, which the late Artifices and ſhiftings of our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries have enforced the Divines of our Church to obſerve and publiſh; after ſo many vehement Proteſtations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the reality of any ſuch diſtinction, and confident aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the entire Conformity between the Doctrine of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or rather ſome few Emiſſaries of it, and that of the immediately precedent Ages, ſo many new Syſtems, Repreſentations and Expoſitions of the pretended Catholick Doctrine; it might have been juſtly expected that the Faith and Doctrine, if not of the preſent and precedent Age, yet at leaſt of all National Churches at this day in Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould be perfectly conformable and inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable. For the Opinions of the precedent Age may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed falſly repreſented to us, the truth of them may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured by cunning Artifices and Illuſions, or evaded by a bold and obſtinate Denial; but the Doctrines and Practice of the preſent Time cannot be diſſembled, nor without too manifeſt an affront to Truth, be denied by theſe Gentlemen of the Miſſion, who may perhaps confound our Reaſon, but can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver delude our Senſes.</p>
            <p>That this diſtinction is both juſt and real, needs no other Argument, than the known and confeſs'd diſtinction between <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Popery. For, ſince the Patrons and Defenders of both theſe Parties appeal to the belief of the Church in the precedent Age; ſince both propoſe Tradition as the Rule of their Faith, and challenge to themſelves the Conſent and Suffrage of that Rule; ſince both their Pleas cannot be allowed, and one Party muſt neceſſarily have departed from the true, ancient, and genuine Popery; it evidently follows, that as one
<pb facs="tcp:61558:3"/> Party conſerves the <hi>Old,</hi> ſo the other hath framed a <hi>New</hi> ſort of Popery. I know it is commonly pretended that theſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences are of ſmall moment, neither eſſential to Chriſtianity, nor to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that either ſide may be ſafely believed, and neither renders any Man either leſs Orthodox, or more Heretical. But certainly theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences are no other than Proteſtations againſt matters of Faith, ſince not only the Subjects of theſe different Doctrines are Matters of the greateſt moment and concern, but attended with all the ſolemn Characters and evident Marks of the moſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentous Articles of Faith; I mean an infinite Zeal and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of each Party for the defence and propagation of their own Opinion, and condemning the contrary Doctrine as a Crime worthy of Excommunication and <hi>Anathema,</hi> which are never ſuppoſed to be inflicted on Opinions of an indifferent na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and free from all Contagion of Hereſy or Schiſm.</p>
            <p>If then the Pope and <hi>Italian</hi> Divines will not allow thoſe of <hi>France</hi> to be truly Orthodox and Catholick, if they think them unworthy and incapable of Eccleſiaſtical Dignities and Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and daily iſſue out Excommunications againſt ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices as the Church of <hi>France</hi> is manifeſtly known to act, allow and command; if on the other ſide, the <hi>French</hi> Clergy ſo far return the Accuſation as to attaint the Pope of Hereſy, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Cenſures raſh, unchriſtian and deſtructive of the Church, and himſelf <hi>ipſo facto</hi> excommunicate; certainly we muſt renounce all Senſe and Reaſon to imagined theſe to be no more than verbal Differences, Scholaſtick Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Opinions of private Divines, which may be ſafely either rejected or received. That Differences of this nature have aroſe between the Church of <hi>France</hi> and See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe continued with great Heat and Animoſity through ſeveral Ages, is manifeſt both from Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Hiſtory. This indeed our Adverſaries deny, but ſurely by the aſſiſtance of that wonderful Secret which can enable them confidently to propoſe the greateſt Contradictions and Falſities, and then effectually ſecure them from bluſhing at them. The Violence and Cruelties practiſed upon many thouſand Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of <hi>France</hi> have been acted within a few Months in the view of the World and the face of Mankind; yet there are not wanting who decry all Relations of theſe Cruelties and
<pb facs="tcp:61558:3"/> Barbarities as the Calumnies and Fictions of Hereticks, and have added this to the other glorious Titles of <hi>Lovis le Grand,</hi> that he hath reduced his Subjects to the Profeſſion of one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by methods of Mercy and Gentleneſs. The preſent differences between the Courts of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous ſoever, might have ſuffered the ſame fate, and with equal Reaſon have been denied; if Monſieur <hi>Barillon,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador, had not, by endeavouring to vindicate his Maſter's Honour and the Juſtice of his Cauſe, obliged us with an Account of the Proceedings of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> upon the Pope's Bull; an Account which as it is undeniable and unexceptionable to our Adverſaries, ſo it abundantly evinceth what I have hitherto advanced.</p>
            <p>The whole Church of <hi>France,</hi> and after them the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> have within a few Years defined and aſſerted the Fallibility of the Pope; and herein acted conſonantly to the Principles and Doctrines of their Anceſtors, who had conſtantly taught the ſame Doctrine, but never ſolemnly defined it. However, this Article is beyond the <hi>Alpes</hi> rejected with a no leſs contrary Zeal, and Infallibility of the Pope ranked among the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Doctrines of the Chriſtian Religion. For proof of this we need go no farther than the forementioned Account of the Proceedings of the Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> which aſſures us, that not only the <hi>Italian</hi> Doctors and Emiſſaries of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> are employed carefully to propagate the Opinion of the Papal Infallibility, as if the belief of that Point were wanting to render <hi>France</hi> truly Catholick; but alſo that one third of the Epiſcopal Sees of <hi>France</hi> being now vacant, and the King having nominated to them ſome of thoſe who aſſiſted at the late Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Aſſembly, wherein the Papal Infallibility was rejected, Perſons as well recommendable for their Piety and Vertue as for their Knowledg and Learning, the Pope refuſeth to grant Bulls of Confirmation to them on pretence that they do not make Profeſſion of a ſound or Orthodox Doctrine, becauſe they do<note place="margin">Pag. 5, 23.</note> not believe him to be Infallible, nor like the <hi>Italian</hi> Doctors, attribute to him the Title of Univerſal Monarch. Which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently demonſtrates, that the Papal Infallibility is eſteemed a neceſſary Doctrine in <hi>Italy,</hi> and the denial of it incompatible with a ſound and Orthodox Belief of the Catholick Faith; ſince Scholaſtick Niceties were never known to incapacitate
<pb facs="tcp:61558:4"/> Men for Eccleſiaſtical Preferments, or caſt them out of the number of Orthodox Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The Primacy of the Pope is a matter of no leſs moment. How far it extends is indeed controverted among Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks; but that ſome Power was aſſigned by Chriſt to St. <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſors over all Members of the Chriſtian Church, is the common Principle of all, propoſed by them as the only Center of Unity, and a Doctrine neceſſarily to be received by all Catholicks. Whatſoever this Power is, it being of Divine Inſtitution, cannot be annulled or reſtrained by any General Council, much leſs by the Laws and Edicts of the Civil Power, but may be exerciſed independently from both. If then any Church refuſeth any Obedience or Submiſſion to the Commands of the Pope, unleſs they be conformable to the Canons of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and ratified in the firſt place by the Civil Power; they thereby declare an intire Disbelief of any Power committed to the Pope by Divine Inſtitution. For however they may pretend Councils to be Infallible, and conſequently inerrable in fixing the limits of the Papal Power (although even according to this ſuppoſition the Papal Power not being antecedent to General Councils, could have no exiſtence in the three firſt Centuries, when no ſuch Councils were held) yet this Infallibility cannot be pretended to be inherent in the Civil Power. The Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prince may poſſibly be an Atheiſt, an Apoſtate, or an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick; may forbid all Obedience to be paid even to the moſt juſt Commands of the Pope, and deny to ratify ſuch Orders as do naturally flow from the execution of that Commiſſion which Chriſt hath given to the Pope. If the Pope hath indeed any ſuch Divine Commiſſion, he may and ought to execute it in ſpight of all oppoſition of the Civil Power; and if he exceeds not the bounds of his Commiſſion, he ought to be obeyed by all faithful Chriſtians, although the Civil Power, far from ratifying his Commands, ſhould even forbid them to be obeyed. No pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg can exempt us from this Duty, nor any humane Law diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with the Obligation of it: yet the Church of <hi>France</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, and conſtantly averrs that no Obedience is due to any Commands of the Pope of what nature ſoever, until they be firſt ratified and confirmed by their Prince. This pretence was not ſtarted of late, but hath been introduced and continued for ſeveral Ages, being the grand Principle of the ſo much famed
<pb facs="tcp:61558:4"/> Liberties of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, a Principle which can no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be maintained than by diſowning and diſclaiming all Divine Inſtitution of the leaſt Papal Power; and accordingly we are told in this account that the boundleſs and arbitrary Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Pope hath been the Source of almoſt all the incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable miſchief with which the Church is afflicted; that his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<note place="margin">Pag. 13, 15, 22, 9.</note> reacheth no farther than the Dioceſs of <hi>Rome,</hi> and his Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archſhip than the neighbouring Provinces ſtiled <hi>Suburbicarian;</hi> that it would be very advantageous that all Eccleſiaſtical Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were tranſacted in the Kingdom, without ever being obliged to have recourſe to <hi>Rome;</hi> and that an Ambaſſador of <hi>France,</hi> executing his Maſter's Orders, cannot thereby incur Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Cenſures; although none will deny that Ambaſſadour may poſſibly in obedience to his Maſter's Commands oppoſe even that Authority of the Pope, which was lawfully inveſted in him by Chriſt, if any ſuch there be.</p>
            <p>But not only doth the Church of <hi>France</hi> hereby diſown the Divine Inſtitution of any Papal Power, not only doth ſhe declare the Thunders of the <hi>Vatican</hi> to have nothing formidable, to be tranſitory Fires, which exhale into Smoke, and do neither hurt<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> pag. 19.</note> nor prejudice ſave to thoſe who darted them; but affirms the Pope to be a Favourer and Patron of Hereticks, <hi>ipſo facto</hi> excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and no Member, much leſs Head, of the Catholick Church. He is accuſed to have maintained converſe and correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence with the condemned Diſciples of <hi>Janſenius,</hi> ever ſince<note place="margin">Pag. 27.</note> he hath been ſeated in S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, to have ſpoken in the higheſt degree in their praiſe, and declared himſelf their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd thereby ſo far to have endangered the Peace of the Church, that nothing leſs than the foreſight and cares of <hi>Lovis le Grand</hi> could reſtore or conſerve it: that he favours the <hi>Quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> and connives at their Hereſy; underhand eſpouſeth their Party, and protects their Perſons. He is denounced Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate upon this ground, That he who without lawful cauſe, and through humane motives, undertakes to ſuſpend one of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Jeſus Chriſt, from the Communion of the Church, doth<note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> ſeparate himſelf from it by ſuch an unjuſt Attempt. Nay far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is declared by the ill exerciſe of his Power, to have loſt<note place="margin">Pag. 37.</note> the Power of binding and unbinding, and thereby in effect to have fallen from the Papacy and to be depoſed. Alas, that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> XI, whom our Miſſionaries repreſent to us as the grand
<pb facs="tcp:61558:5"/> Pattern of Apoſtolick Vertue and Holineſs, ſhould at laſt be convicted of Hereſy, and proved to be no Member of the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He hardly eſcaped laſt year from being condemned as a <hi>Quietiſt</hi> in the Inquiſition of <hi>Rome;</hi> and now, (alas poor Man!) inſtead of enjoying that Honour, which he hath ſo ambitiouſly courted, of ſuffering Martyrdom in defence of the Church, he may perhaps be burnt for an Heretick, as ſoon as <hi>Lovis le Grand</hi> ſhall pleaſe<note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> to execute that Right, which he pretends to have to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf known in the quality of his Sovereign.</p>
            <p>It cannot be pretended that theſe are matters of light moment in themſelves, but unhappily at this time heightned into great differences by the ill Conduct and falſe Zeal of an ignorant and ſtupid Pope; ſince his Actions are grounded upon, and upheld by the famous Bull <hi>in Coenâ Domini:</hi> which himſelf refers to, and the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> upon that account decrieth with ſo much indignation, telling us, that if this Decree, whereby the Popes declare themſelves Sovereign Monarchs of the World, be legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate,<note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> the Majeſty Royal will then depend upon their humour, all their Liberties will be aboliſhed; the Secular Judges will no longer have the Power to try the poſſeſſion of Benefices, nor the civil and criminal Cauſe of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons. All this is indeed literally true, and the natural conſequence of that Bull. But then this alone abundantly manifeſts the Juſtice of our Charge, and the real difference of the Doctrines of the Churches of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> in matters of the greateſt moment. In <hi>France</hi> this Bull is eſteemed impious, unjuſt, and uncanonical, deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the Rights of Princes and Priviledges of national Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, contrary to the Laws, and deſtructive of the Chriſtian Church. At <hi>Rome</hi> it is accounted ſacred and inviolable, ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confirmed by more than twenty Popes, whoſe Names and Conſtitutions are prefixed to the Bull, publiſhed with the greateſt Solemnity imaginable every <hi>Maunday Thurſday,</hi> the Infringers and Violators of it declared <hi>ipſo facto</hi> excommunicate, and Priviledges and Diſpenſations to the contrary annulled and made void; and all this, as the Preface of the Bull aſſureth us, to preſerve the Unity and Integrity of the Faith, to teach all private Chriſtians what they are certainly to believe, and by preventing their Fluctuation and Miſtakes in Faith, to ſecure to them the attainment of eternal Salvation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61558:5"/>
            <p>After this Bull hath been Enacted and confirmed by ſo many Popes, promulged ſo often and ſo ſolemnly, ſo exactly executed and put in practiſe by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> propoſed as the Standard of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctrine, and appealed to by this preſent Pope in the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies depending between him and the Court of <hi>France;</hi> it cannot be any longer doubted that all matters whether of belief or practiſe contained in it are eſteemed neceſſary to Salvation by the particular Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> This alſo the puniſhments annexed to it evidently demonſtrates, Excommunication and Anathema being <hi>ipſo facto</hi> incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the violation of any part of it. For the very nature of theſe Excommunications ſuppoſeth that the perſons offending do by that very act ceaſe to be Chriſtians or Catholicks, and diſown themſelves to be ſo, and that the action to which this puniſhment is declared to be annexed, is directly contrary to Faith, and deſtructive of it. If after all, the Doctrines of this Bull be denied to be juſtly charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> it might with equal reaſon be pretended that the ancient Commonwealth of <hi>Rome</hi> could not be juſtly accuſed of Idolatry, or the worſhip of falſe gods, altho ſhe eſtabliſhed that worſhip with ſevere Laws, maintained the exerciſe of it with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Revenues, puniſht the neglect of it with great ſtrictneſs and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and made her addreſſes to thoſe falſe Deities upon all great oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions and affairs of State; becauſe ſome few Philoſophers oppoſed the general opinion, contemned their Ceremonies, and diſapproved their worſhip.</p>
            <p>Many and large Obſervations might be drawn from this Bull diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the preſent Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But I will here take notice of no more than two. And firſt, Popery is commonly repreſented by the Reformed Divines as injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Rights of Princes, and promoting Sedition and Rebellion. That the lawfulneſs of the Depoſition of Princes hath been often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by Popes and Councils, and put in practice by them, cannot be denied; but then it is pretended that it was not defined dogmatically, nor as a matter of faith, that their definitions are miſrepreſented by us, and were never received nor allowed by the Univerſal Church. However the juſtice of our Charge is ſufficiently manifeſted by this Bull, which aſſerteth and maintaineth the Independency of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy from the Secular Prince, by forbidding the Civil Power to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, impriſon, vex, ſummon, tax, fine, or exerciſe any Act of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over Eccleſiaſtical perſons, upon pain of Excommunication and Anathema. Now Depoſition of Princes by the Papal Authority, and exemption of the Clergy from any obedience to them, by reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:61558:6"/> of their immediate ſubjection to the Pope, being both founded upon the ſame principle of injuſtice and uſurpation, do mutually infer each other. Nay to exempt the whole Clergy from the obedience of their Natural Prince, doth actually deveſt him of all authority of one part of his ſubjects, and deprive him of one half of his Kingdom, eſpecially in thoſe Countries where the Clergy and Regulars are vaſtly numer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as in all places where Popery obtains, or where they poſſeſs a great part of the Revenues of the Kingdom; the Secular Prince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only forbidden to impoſe any Taxes upon the Clergy, or their Revenues, but alſo even to receive them when voluntarily offered without an expreſs Licenſe from the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> If after all this the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Emiſſaries will pretend to true and real Loyalty, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg their ſubjection to their Natural Prince, they muſt firſt own themſelves to be Excommunicated perſons, and lay down the name of <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks. But we have reaſon to believe that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionaries intend no ſuch acknowledgment; ſince they have with ſo much pomp lately revived the Feſtival of St. <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> who died in defence of this Trayterous Poſition, That the Clergy owe no Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Secular Power.</p>
            <p>In the next place it may be obſerved, that the greateſt part of this Bull is employed in Excommunicating and Anathemat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zing all thoſe who any ways preſume to intermeddle in the cognizance of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical matters, or interrupt the proceedings of Eccleſiaſtical Courts by Prohibitions, Appeals, or any Evaſions of the like nature; or who give aid, advice, or conſent thereto. All this is worded with ſuch ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous nicety and exactneſs; that it is impoſſible to be avoided by any ſubtile Evaſions, and then the Excommunication incurred can be taken off and abſolved only by the Pope himſelf, except at the point of death, and then only when eminent ſigns of true repentance and aſſurance of full ſatisfaction are given. Notwithſtanding ſuch expreſs prohibition and denunciation of Anathema's, it is notoriouſly known that all Popiſh Princes do intermeddle in judging Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes; that particularly in <hi>France</hi> the Spiritual Courts are almoſt wholly rendred uſeleſs and debarred from exerciſing their Authority by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Prohibitions from the Secular Court, and that in <hi>Sicily</hi> all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Matters and Cauſes are decided by the ſole Authority of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and his Commiſſioners; not to mention examples and practiſes of the like nature in other Popiſh Countries. From whence it follows that by vertue of this Bull all theſe Princes, their Counſellors, Parliaments, Lawyers, and Adherents, together with all who procure, execute or conſent to theſe Prohibitions and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments
<pb facs="tcp:61558:6"/> of Eccleſiaſtical Juſtice, ſtand Excommunicate by the Pope, and are really no Members of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No Priviledg or Exemption can in this caſe be drawn from anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Immunities, Pragmaticks or Concordats, which the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſo much inſiſt on; ſince the Bull proceeds with a <hi>Non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante</hi> to all theſe, and declares them Null, whenſoever they oppoſe the Contents of the Bull. Nay, decreeth that whoever recurs to them, thereby to elude the Obligation of the Bull, ſhall thereby <hi>ipſo Facto</hi> become Excommunicate, altho he ſhould in no other caſe have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred that Puniſhment. In vain, therefore doth the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> oppoſe the Liberties of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, the Pragmatick of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and Concordat of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XI. and <hi>Francis</hi> to the preſent Attempts of the Pope, and his Excommunication of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Lavardin.</hi> For the Pope having wiſely grounded his Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon the Bull <hi>in Caena Domini,</hi> which annuls and aboliſheth them all, the Parliament muſt either forego their Plea, or their pretence of retaining Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> By the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice the Pope hath cut off the Advocates Appeal to a future Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. For the Bull declareth that all who make, admit, favour, or countenance any ſuch Appeal, ſhall incur Excommunication. Thus alſo the Argument of the Invalidity of the Excommunication of the Embaſſador, drawn from the Omiſſion of his Name in the Papal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, falls to ground. For the Bull hath particularly provided for this Caſe, and decreeth that all Violators of it, of what Dignity ſoever, ſhall be as effectually Excommunicated, as if they had been particularly named in it.</p>
            <p>If then all the Violators of this Bull, are <hi>ipſo Facto</hi> Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; and all, or at leaſt almoſt all the Popiſh Princes of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> together with the greateſt part of their Subjects, are open and manifeſt Violators of it, it follows that we have very falſe Notions of Popery, when we imagine it a large and diffuſive Sect; that vaſt and numerous Schiſms are entertained, and lay undiſcerned in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> that the Primacy of the Pope inſtead of being the Center of Unity, is indeed the Fountain of Schiſm; and that among many Papiſts, there are few Catholicks. For if, as our Adverſaries commonly define it, the Catholick Church be the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all Chriſtians in Communion with the particular Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſoever are Excommunicated by the Pope, ceaſe to be in Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and conſequently in their Opinion, ceaſe to be Catholicks. They may indeed ſtill remain Members of the truly Catholick Church; but then a true Notion of
<pb facs="tcp:61558:7"/> Catholick Church muſt be allowed, and the former muſt be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded. But then the Church of <hi>England</hi> may alſo put in her claim for Catholick, and the grand Argument of our Adverſaries againſt her Reformation, will be totally diſſolved. However it manifeſtly appears that this Bull hath ſhut moſt Papiſts out of the Boſom of the Church, and reduced the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to very narrow Limits.</p>
            <p>Whenever, therefore our zealous Miſſionaries exaggerate to us the extent of their Church, and urge the glorious Title of Amplitude in favour of it, we may juſtly reject it; it not certainly appearing, who may be properly called <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, ſince this, and other Bulls of the like Nature, which inflict <hi>ipſo Facto</hi> Excommunications, deprive vaſt numbers of Men, whole Societies, and perhaps King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, of Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> or if we in any manner allow their Argument, we muſt firſt require them to ſubſtract from their account all whom the Pope in this Bull doth Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, and thereby puts in the ſame Condition with <hi>Turks, Infidels,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks.</hi> We have one requeſt more to them, that to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Converſion of three Kingdoms, they would obtain of the Pope an Abolition of this Bull, or at leaſt of that Clauſe of it, which Excommunicates all Secular Perſons who poſſeſs Church Lands. For ſince out of the abundance of their Generoſity they have been pleaſed to aſſure to us the quiet Poſſeſſion of Abby-Lands, it remains to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat their kindneſs, that they ſet us right in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as that of <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> Otherwiſe it will be an eternal Obſtacle to the Converſion of the Poſſeſſors of theſe Lands, if the Curſes of our Holy Father the Pope, be plentifully ſhowred down upon them every <hi>Maunday-Thurſday;</hi> and they muſt entruſt their Souls to the Pope for no other end, than that he may deliver them up to the Devil.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61558:7"/>
            <head>Ex Bullario Laertii Cherubini, Romae 1638. TOM. III. p. 183.</head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="excerpt_from_papal_bull">
                           <head>
                              <hi>Conſtitutio Pauli</hi> V. 63.</head>
                           <p>EXcommunicatio &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathematizatio quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Haeretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, eorum<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum ac Schiſmaticorum, vel Eccleſiaſticam Libertatem laedentium, aut quoquo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do diſpoſitis in hac Bulla, de more in die Caena Domini publicare ſolita, contraveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Quoad omnia quaſi Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula hujus Bullae (ultra Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagan. 3. <hi>Pauli</hi> II. &amp; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagan. 5. <hi>Sixti</hi> IV. in tit. de Paenitentia &amp; Remiſſioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus) habes ſupra Conſtitut. 1. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbani</hi> V. <hi>fol.</hi> 215. Conſtitut. 25. <hi>Julii</hi> II. <hi>f.</hi> 482. Conſtitut. 10. <hi>Pauli</hi> III. <hi>f.</hi> 522. necnon Conſtitut. 81. <hi>Gregorii</hi> XIII. <hi>f.</hi> 348. <hi>l.</hi> 2. Aliorum autem Bullas ejuſmodi Caenae Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni nuncupatas volens praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſi, his duntaxat contentus,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61558:8"/> ex quibus pro temporum conditione Romanos Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aliquid immutaſſe cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur. Non tamen poſtha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bui proxime indicandas, uti apprime neceſſarias, &amp; ſuper hujus Bullae capitibus ſpecia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter editas.</p>
               <p>Extat ergo in hoc Opere ſpecialis edita ſanctio <hi>Nicolai</hi> III. circa § primum hujus Bullae in ejus Conſt. 2. ſup. <hi>fol.</hi> 143. &amp; circa § 2. extat Conſt. 5. <hi>Pii</hi> II. <hi>f.</hi> 290. <hi>l.</hi> 1. Circa § 4. extat Conſt. 7. <hi>Pii</hi> V. <hi>f. 137. l.</hi> 2. Circa § 7. extat Conſt. 3. <hi>Nicolai</hi> V. <hi>f. 283. l.</hi> 1. Circa § 10. extat Canon <hi>Calliſti</hi> I. in <hi>c.</hi> 23. cauſ. 24. <hi>q.</hi> 3. Circa § 11. reſpectu Cardinalium extat Conſt. 16. <hi>Leonis</hi> X. <hi>f. 420. l.</hi> 1. &amp; alia 93. <hi>Pii</hi> V. <hi>f. 222. l.</hi> 2. Circa § 12 extat Conſt. 11. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andri</hi> VI. <hi>f.</hi> 352. Circa § 14. extat Conſt. 2. <hi>Martini</hi> V. <hi>f.</hi> 239 &amp; alia 17. <hi>Innocentii</hi> VIII. <hi>f.</hi> 343. ac altera 30. <hi>Leonis</hi> X. <hi>f.</hi> 440. necnon alia 39. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis</hi> VII. <hi>f. 505. l.</hi> 1. &amp; altera 19. <hi>Gregorii</hi> XIII. <hi>f.</hi> 290.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61558:8"/> 
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2. Circa § 15. multi ſunt Canones in Corpore Juris, &amp; extat Conſt. 10. <hi>Martini</hi> V. f. 247. Circa § 19. extat Conſt. 3. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbani</hi> VI. f. 222. Et Circa § 20. extat Conſt. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Joannis</hi> XXII. <hi>f.</hi> 174. &amp; alia 3. <hi>Clementis</hi> VI. <hi>f.</hi> 212. alia 13. <hi>Leonis</hi> X. <hi>f.</hi> 314. &amp; altera 11. <hi>Pauli</hi> IV. <hi>f.</hi> 595.</p>
               <p>Alia hujuſmodi Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatio in die Coenae Domini Promulgari ſolita eſt in S. D. N. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbani</hi> VIII. Conſt. 62. Paſtoralis infr. Tom. 4.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                     <body>
                        <div type="papal_bull">
                           <head>Paulus Epiſcopus, Servus Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorum Dei, ad perpetuam rei memoriam.</head>
                           <p>PAſtoralis <hi>Romani</hi> Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis vigilantia &amp; ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citudo, cum in omni Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae Chriſtianae pace &amp; tranquillitate procuranda pro fui muneris officio aſſidue verſatur, tum potiſſimum in Catholicae fidei ſine qua im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibile
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61558:9"/> eſt placere Deo, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate at<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> integritate retinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, maxime elucet: Nimirum ut fideles Chriſti non ſint parvuli fluctuantes, ne<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumferantur omni vento doctrinae in nequitia homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ad circumventionem erroris, ſed omnes occurrant in unitate fidei &amp; agnitionis Filii Dei in virum perfectum, ne<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> ſe in hujus vitae ſocietate &amp; communione laedant, aut inter ſe alter alteri offenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem praebeat, ſed potius in vinculo caritatis conjuncti, tanquam unius corporis membra ſub Chriſto capite, ejuſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> in terris Vicario <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano</hi> Pontifice Beatiſſimi <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri</hi> Succeſſore, a quo totius Eccleſiae unitas dimanat, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantur in aedificatione, at<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> ita divina gratia adjutrice ſic praeſentis vitae quiete gaude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, ut ſutura quoque beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine perfruantur. Ob quas ſane cauſas <hi>Romani</hi> Pontifices praedeceſſores noſtri hodierna die, quae anniverſaria Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicaeCoenae commemoratione ſolennis eſt, ſpiritualem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticae diſciplinae gladium, &amp; ſalutaria juſtitiae arma per miniſterium ſummi Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61558:9"/> ad Dei gloriam &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum ſalutem ſolenniter exercere conſueverunt. Nos igitur, quibus nihil optabilius eſt, quam fidei inviolatam integritatem, publicam Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem &amp; Juſtitiam, deo autore, tueri, vetuſtum &amp; ſolennem hunc morem ſequentes;</p>
                           <p>§. 1. Excommunicamus &amp; anathematizamus ex parte Dei Omnipotentis, Patris &amp; Filii &amp; Spiritus Sancti, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritate quoque Beatorum Apoſtolorum <hi>Petri</hi> &amp; <hi>Pauli,</hi> ac noſtra, quoſcunque Huſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, Vuichlephiſtas, Lutera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Zuinglianos, Calvini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas, Ugonottos, Anabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas, Trinitarios, &amp; a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana fide Apoſtatas, ac om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſingulos alios Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, quocunque nomine cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeantur, &amp; cujuſcunque ſectae exiſtant; ac eis credentes, eorumque receptatores, fauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; generaliter quoſlibet illorum defenſores; ac eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundem libros haereſin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentes, vel de Religione tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantes ſine auctoritate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61558:10"/> &amp; Sedis Apoſtolicae ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter legentes aut retinentes, imprimentes, ſeu quomodoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let defendentes, ex quavis cauſa publice vel occulte, quovis ingenio vel colore; necnon Schiſmaticos &amp; eos qui ſe a noſtra &amp; <hi>Romani</hi> Pontificis pro tempore exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentis obedientia pertinaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubtrahunt vel recedunt.</p>
                           <p>§ 2. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes &amp; ſingulos, cujuſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſtatus, gradus, ſeu condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis fuerint, Univerſitates Collegia &amp; Capitula, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque nomine nuncupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, interdicimus, ab ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus ſeu mandatis noſtris ac <hi>Romanorum</hi> Pontificum pro tempore exiſtentium ad Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſale futurum Concilium appellantes; necnon eos quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum auxilio vel favore appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum fuerit.</p>
                           <p>§ 3. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes Piratas, Curſarios ac Latrunculos Maritimos, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currentes Mare noſtrum, praecipue a Monte <hi>Argenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> uſque ad <hi>Terraciuam,</hi> ac omnes eorum fautores, recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatores &amp; defenſores.</p>
                           <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61558:10"/>
                           <p>§. 4. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes &amp; ſingulos, qui Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum quorumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vibus tempeſtate, ſeu in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſum (ut dici ſolet) jacta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, vel quoquo modo nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragium paſſis, ſeu in ipſis navibus, ſive ex eiſdem ejecta in Mare, vel in littore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venta, cujuſcunque generis bona, tam in noſtris, <hi>Tyrrheni</hi> &amp; <hi>Adriatici,</hi> quam in caeteris cujuſque Maris regionibus &amp; littoribus, ſurripuerint; ita ut nec ob quodcunque Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium, Conſuetudinem, aut longiſſimi etiam immemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis temporis poſſeſſionem, ſeu alium quemcunque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textum excuſari poſſint.</p>
                           <p>§ 5. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes qui in terris ſuis nova Pedagia ſeu Gabellas, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terquam in caſibus ſibi a jure, ſeu ex ſpeciali ſedis Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae licentia permiſſis, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunt vel augent, ſeu imponi vel augeri prohibita exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt.</p>
                           <p>§ 6. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes falſarios literarum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicarum, etiam in forma
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61558:11"/> Brevis, ac<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Supplicationum, Gratiam vel Juſtitiam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernentium, per <hi>Romanum</hi> Pontiſicem vel <hi>S. R. E.</hi> Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancellarios ſeu gerentes vices eorum, aut de mandato ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Pontificis ſignatarum, necnon falſo publicantes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teras Apoſtolicas, etiam in forma Brevis, &amp; etiam falſo ſignantes Supplicationes hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi ſub nomine <hi>Romani</hi> Pontificis ſeu Vicecancellarii, aut gerentium vices praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum.</p>
                           <p>§ 7. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes illos, qui ad <hi>Sarace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Turcas,</hi> &amp; alios Chriſtiani nominis hoſtes, &amp; inimicos, vel Haereticos per noſtras vel hujus Sanctae Sedis ſententias expreſſe vel nominatim de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratos deferunt ſeu tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittunt Equos, Arma, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, filum Ferri, Stannum, Chalybem, omniaque Metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum genera atque Bellica Inſtrumenta, Lignamina, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>napem, Funes, tam ex ipſo Canape quam alia quacunque materia, &amp; ipſam materiam, aliaque hujuſmodi, quibus Chriſtianos &amp; Catholicos impugnant; necnon illos qui
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61558:11"/> per ſe vel per alios de rebus ſtatum Chriſtianae Reipubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae concernentibus, in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum perniciem &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ipſos <hi>Turcas</hi> &amp; Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Religionis inimicos, nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Haereticos, in damnum Catholicae Religionis, certio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res faciunt, illiſque ad id auxilium conſilium vel favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem quomodolibet praeſtant. Non obſtantibus quibuſcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Privilegiis, quibuſvis Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Principibus, Rebuſ-pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis, per Nos &amp; Sedem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictam hactenus conceſſis, de hujuſmodi prohibitione ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſam mentionem non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientibus.</p>
                           <p>§ 8. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes impedientes ſeu inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes eos, qui victualia ſeu alia ad uſum <hi>Romanae</hi> Curiae neceſſaria adducunt, ac etiam eos qui ne ad <hi>Romanam</hi> Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am adducantur vel afferantur prohibent, impediunt ſeu perturbant, ſeu haec facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes defendunt per ſe vel per alios, cujuſcunque fuerint ordinis, praeeminentiae, condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis &amp; ſtatus, etiamſi Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificali ſeu Regali aut alia quavis Eccleſiaſtica vel mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dana
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61558:12"/> praefulgeant dignitate.</p>
                           <p>§ 9. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes illos, qui ad ſedem Apoſtolicam venientes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentes ab eadem, ſua vel aliorum opera interficiunt, mutilant, ſpoliant, capiunt, detinent; necnon illos omnes qui juriſdictionem ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vel delegatam a nobis vel noſtris Judicibus non haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, illam ſibi temere vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantes, ſimilia contra mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes in eadem Curia audent perpetrare.</p>
                           <p>§ 10. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes interficientes, muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes, vulnerantes, detinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, capientes ſeu depraedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Romipetas ſeu Perigrinos ad Urbem cauſa Devotionis ſeu Peregrinationis acceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; in ea morantes, vel ab ipſa recedentes, &amp; in his dantes auxilium, conſilium, vel favorem.</p>
                           <p>§ 11. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes interficientes, vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes, mutilantes, percu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientes, capientes, carceran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, detinentes, vel hoſtiliter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61558:12"/> inſequentes <hi>S. R. E.</hi> Cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ac Patriarchas, Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopos, Epiſcopos, Sediſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Apoſtolicae Legatos vel nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cios, aut eos a ſuis Diaeceſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Territoriis, Terris, ſeu Dominiis ejicientes, necnon ea mandantes vel rata ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentes, ſeu praeſtantes in eis auxilium, conſilium, vel fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorem.</p>
                           <p>§ 12. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes illos, qui per ſe vel per alios, perſonas Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticas quaſcunque, vel ſecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ad <hi>Romanam</hi> Curiam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eorum cauſis &amp; negotiis recurrentes, ac illa in eadem Curia proſequentes aut pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curantes, negotiorumque ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores, advocatos, procuratores &amp; agentes, ſeu etiam Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores vel Judices ſuper dictis cauſis vel negotiis deputatos, occaſione cauſarum vel nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum hujuſmodi, occidunt, ſeu quoquo modo percutiunt, bonis ſpoliant; ſeu qui per ſe vel per alios, directe vel indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte delicta hujuſmodi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere, exequi vel procurare, aut in eiſdem auxilium, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium vel favorem praeſtare non verentur, cujuſcunque
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61558:13"/> praeeminentiae &amp; dignitatis fuerint.</p>
                           <p>§ 13. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes tam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Eccleſiaſticos quam Seculares, cujuſcunque dignitatis, qui praetexentes frivolam quandam appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem a gravamine vel futura executione literarum Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarum etiam in forma Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis, tam gratiam quam juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam concernentium, necnon citationum, inhibitionum, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrorum, monitoriorum, proceſſuum, executorialium, &amp; aliorum Decretorum, a Nobis &amp; Sede praedicta ſeu Legatis, Nunciis Praeſidenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Palatii noſtri &amp; Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae Apoſtolicae Auditoribus, Commiſſariis, aliiſque Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus &amp; delegatis Apoſtolicis emanatorum, &amp; quae pro tempore emanaverint, aut alias ad Curias Saeculares &amp; Laicam poteſtatem recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, &amp; ab ea inſtante etiam Fiſci Procuratore &amp; Advoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, appellationes hujuſmodi admitti, ac literas, citatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, inhibitiones, ſequeſtra, monitoria, &amp; alia praedicta, capi &amp; retineri faciunt. Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve illa ſimpliciter, vel ſine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61558:13"/> eorum beneplacito &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſu vel examine executioni demandari, aut ne Tabellio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; Notarii ſuper hujuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di literarum &amp; proceſſuum executione, inſtrumenta vel acta conficere, aut confecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parti cujus intereſt, tradere debeant, impediunt vel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibent, ac etiam partes ſeu eorum agentes, conſanguine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os, affines, familiares, nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios, executores, &amp; ſub-exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutores literarum, citatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, monitoriorum, &amp; alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum praedictorum capiunt, percutiunt, vulnerant, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerant, detinent, ex Civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, Locis, &amp; Regnis ejici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, bonis ſpoliant, perterre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faciunt, concutiunt &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minantur per ſe vel per ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſeu alios, publice vel oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culte; quive alias quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque perſonis in genere vel in ſpecie, ne pro quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis eorum negotiis profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendis ſeu gratiis vel literis impetrandis ad <hi>Romanam</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam accedant, aut recurſum habeant, ſeu gratias ipſas vel literas a dicta Sede impetrent ſeu impetratis utantur, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte vel indirecte prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, ſtatuere ſeu mandare,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61558:14"/> vel eas apud ſe aut Notarios ſeu Tabelliones, vel alias quomodolibet retinere prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumunt.</p>
                           <p>§ 14. Item excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; anathematizamus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſingulos, qui per ſe vel alios, auctoritate propria ac de facto, quarumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum vel aliarum gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; literarum Apoſtolica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum praetextu, beneficiales, &amp; decimarum, ac alias cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas ſpirituales ac ſpiritualibus annexas, ab Auditoribus &amp; Commiſſariis noſtris, aliiſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Judicibus Eccleſiaſticis avo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant; illarumve curſum &amp; audientiam; ac perſonas, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitula, Conventus, Collegia, cauſas ipſas proſequi volentes impediunt ac ſe de illarum cognitione tanquam Judices interponunt. Quive partes actrices, quae illas committi fecerunt &amp; faciunt, ad revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum &amp; revocari facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum citationes vel inhibitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aut alias literas in eis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretas, &amp; ad faciendum vel
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61558:14"/> conſentiendum eos contra quos tales inhibitiones ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narunt a cenſuris &amp; paenis in illis contentis abſolvi, per ſtatutum vel alias compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt; vel executionem lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum Apoſtolicarum ſeu ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutorialium, proceſſuum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ac decretorum praedictorum quomodolibet impediunt, vel ſuum ad id favorem, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium aut aſſenſum praeſtant, etiam praetextu violentiae prohibendae, vel aliarum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſionum, ſeu etiam, donec ipſi ad nos informandos, ut dicunt, ſupplicaverint aut ſupplicari fecerint; niſi ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicationes hujuſmodi coram Nobis &amp; ſede Apoſtolica legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time proſequantur, etiamſi talia committentes fuerint Praeſidentes Cancellariarum, Conſiliorum, Parlamento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Cancellarii, Vice-can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellarii, Conſiliarii, ordinarii vel extraordinarii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quorum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Principum Saecularium; etiamſi Imperiali, Regali, Ducali, vel alia quacun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> praefulgeant dignitate; aut Archiepiſcopi, Epiſcopi, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, Commendatarii ſeu Vicarii fuerint.</p>
                           <pb n="16" facs="tcp:61558:15"/>
                           <p>§ 15. Quive ex eorum praetenſo officio, vel ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam partis, aut aliorum quorumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> perſonas Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticas, Capitula, Convent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Collegia Eccleſiarum qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> coram ſe ad ſuum Tribunal, Audientiam, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellariam, Conſilium, vel Parlamentum, praeter juris Canonici diſpoſitionem, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hunt, vel trahi faciunt vel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curant, directe vel indirecte, quovis quaeſito colore; nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non qui ſtatuta, ordinationes, conſtitutiones, pragmaticas, ſeu quaevis alia decreta in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere vel in ſpecie, ex quavis cauſa &amp; quovis quaeſito co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lore, ac etiam praetextu cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſvis conſuetudinis &amp; privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii, vel alias quomodolibet fecerint, ordinaverint &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licaverint, vel factis &amp; ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis uſi fuerint, unde liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Eccleſiaſtica tollitur, ſeu in aliquo laeditur vel depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur, aut alio quovis modo reſtringitur, ſeu noſtris &amp; dictae ſedis, ac quarumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> eccleſiarum juribus quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolibet directe vel indirecte, tacite vel expreſſe praejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur.</p>
                           <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61558:15"/>
                           <p>§ 16. Necnon qui Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopos, Epiſcopos, alioſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> ſuperiores &amp; inferiores Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latos, &amp; omnes alios quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Judices Eccleſiaſticos ordinarios quomodolibet hac de cauſa directe vel indirecte, carcerando vel moleſtando eorum agentes, procuratores, familiares necnon conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neos &amp; affines, aut alias im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediunt, quo minus juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione ſua Eccleſiaſtica con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra quoſcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> utantur, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum quod Canones &amp; ſacrae conſtitutiones Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticae, &amp; decreta Conciliorum Generalium, &amp; praeſertim Tridentini, ſtatuunt; ac e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam eos qui poſt ipſorum ordinariorum ac etiam ab eis delegatorum quorumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> ſententias &amp; decreta, aut ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as fori eccleſiaſtici judicium eludentes, ad Cancellarias &amp; alias Curias ſeculares recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, &amp; ab illis prohibitiones &amp; mandata etiam paenalia, ordinariis aut delegatis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictis decerni, &amp; contra illos exequi procurant; eos quo<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> qui haec decernunt &amp; exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quntur, ſeu dant auxilium, conſilium, patrocinium &amp; favorem in eiſdem.</p>
                           <pb n="18" facs="tcp:61558:16"/>
                           <p>§ 17. Quive juriſdictiones ſeu fructus, reditus &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus ad nos &amp; ſedem Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicam, &amp; quaſcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticas perſonas ratione Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiarum, Monaſteriorum &amp; aliorum beneficiorum Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticorum pertinentes uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant, vel etiam quavis oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione vel cauſa ſine Romani Pontificis vel aliorum ad id legitimam facultatem haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium expreſſa licentia ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrant.</p>
                           <p>§ 18. Quive collectas, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimas, talleas, praeſtantias &amp; alia onera Clericis, Praelatis &amp; aliis perſonis Eccleſiaſticis, ac eorum &amp; Eccleſiarum, Monaſteriorum &amp; aliorum beneficiorum Eccleſiaſtico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum bonis, illorumve fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus, reditibus &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventibus hujuſmodi, abſque ſimili Romani Pontificis ſpeciali &amp; expreſſa licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia imponunt, &amp; diverſis etiam exquiſitis modis exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, aut ſic impoſita a ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te dantibus &amp; cóncedentibus recipiunt. Necnon qui per ſe vel alios directe vel indirecte praedicta facere, exequi vel procurare, aut in eiſdem auxilium, conſilium vel favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61558:16"/> praeſtare non verentur, cujuſcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> ſint praeeminentiae, dignitatis, ordinis, conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis aut ſtatus, etiamſi Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riali aut Regali fulgeant dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate; ſeu Principes, Duces, Comites, Barones, &amp; alii Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentatus; quicun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> etiam Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Provinciis, Civitatibus &amp; Terris quoquomodo Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, conſiliarii &amp; Senato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, aut quavis etiam Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficali dignitate inſigniti. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novantes decreta ſuper his per Sacros Canones, tam in <hi>Lateranenſi</hi> noviſſime cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brato, quam aliis Conciliis generalibus edita, etiam cum cenſuris &amp; paenis in eis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis.</p>
                           <p>§ 19. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes &amp; quoſcunque Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus &amp; Judices, Notarios, Scribas, Executores, Subex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutores quomodolibet ſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terponentes in cauſis capita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus ſeu criminalibus contra Perſonas Eccleſiaſticas, illas proceſſando, banniendo, ſeu ſententias contra illas profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo vel exequendo ſine ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciali, ſpecifica &amp; expreſſa hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus Sanctae Sedis Apoſtolicae licentia; quique ejuſmodi li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61558:17"/> ad Perſonas &amp; caſus non expreſſos extendunt, vel alias illa perperam abutuntur, etiamſi talia committentes fuerint Conſiliarii, Senato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Praeſidentes, Cancellarii, Vice-cancellarii, aut quovis alio nomine nuncupati.</p>
                           <p>§ 20. Item, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus &amp; anathematizamus omnes illos, qui per ſe ſeu alios, directe vel indirecte, ſub quocun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> titulo ſeu colore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vadere, deſtruere, occupare &amp; detinere praeſumpſerint, in totum vel in partem Almam Urbem, Regnum <hi>Siciliae,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulas <hi>Sardiniae,</hi> &amp; <hi>Corſicae,</hi> Terras circa <hi>Pharum,</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium B. <hi>Petri</hi> in <hi>Tuſcia,</hi> Ducatum <hi>Spoletanum,</hi> Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum <hi>Venayſinum, Sabinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem, Marchiae, Anconitanae, Maſſae, Trebariae, Romandio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae, Campaniae,</hi> &amp; Maritimas Provincias, illarumque Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras &amp; loca, ac Terras ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis commiſſionis <hi>Arnulforum,</hi> Civitateſque noſtras <hi>Bononi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, Caeſenam, Ariminum, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neventum, Peruſium, Avenio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> Civitatem <hi>Caſtelli, Tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dertum, Ferrariam, Coma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clum,</hi> &amp; alias Civitates, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras &amp; loca, vel jura ad ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61558:17"/> 
                              <hi>Romanam</hi> Eccleſiam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentia, dictae<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> 
                              <hi>Romanae</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae mediate vel immediate ſubjecta, necnon ſupremam juriſdictionem in illis, Nobis &amp; eidem <hi>Romanae</hi> Eccleſiae competentem, de facto uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, perturbare, retinere &amp; vexare variis modis praeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt, necnon adhaerentes, fautores, &amp; defenſores eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſeu illis auxilium, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium vel favorem quomodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet praeſtantes.</p>
                           <p>§ 21. Volentes praeſentes noſtros Proceſſus, ac omnia &amp; quaecunque his literis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenta, quouſque alii hujuſmodi proceſſus a Nobis aut <hi>Romano</hi> Pontifice pro tempore exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtente fiant aut publicentur, durare ſuoſque effectus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino ſortiri.</p>
                           <p>§ 22. Caeterum a praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis ſententiis nullus per ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quam per <hi>Romanum</hi> Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificem, niſi in mortis arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo conſtitutus, nec etiam tunc, niſi de ſtando Eccleſiae mandatis &amp; ſatisfaciendo cautione praeſtita, abſolvi poſſit, etiam praetextu qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumvis facultatum &amp; indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum quibuſcunque perſonis Eccleſiaſticis, ſecularibus, &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61558:18"/> quorumvis Ordinum, etiam Mendicantium, &amp; Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, regularibus, etiam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopali vel alia majori dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate praeditis, ipſiſque Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinibus &amp; eorum Monaſteriis, Conventibus &amp; Domibus ac Capitulis, Collegiis, Confra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitatibus, Congregationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Hoſpitalibus, &amp; locis piis, necnon Laicis, etiamſi Imperiali, Regali, &amp; alia mundana excellentia fulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, per Nos &amp; dictam Sedem ac cujuſvis Concilii decreta, verbo, literis, aut alia quacunque Scriptura in genere &amp; in ſpecie conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum &amp; innovatorum, ac concedendorum &amp; innovan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum.</p>
                           <p>§ 23. Quod ſi forte aliqui contra tenorem praeſentium talibus excommunicatione &amp; anathemate laqueatis, vel eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum alicui abſolutionis bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium impendere de facto praeſumpſerint, eos excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municationis ſententia inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus, gravius contra eos ſpiritualiter &amp; temporaliter, prout expedire noverimus, proceſſuri.</p>
                           <pb n="23" facs="tcp:61558:18"/>
                           <p>§ 24. Declarantes ac pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes quamcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, etiamſi ſolenniter per Nos faciendam, praedictos excommunicatos ſub praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus comprehenſos, niſi pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us a praemiſſis cum vero pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſito ſimilia ulterius non committendi, deſtiterint, ac quoad eos, qui contra eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticam libertatem, ut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, ſtatuta fecerint, niſi prius ſtatuta, ordinationes, conſtitutiones, pragmaticas, &amp; decreta hujuſmodi publice revocaverint, &amp; ex Archivis ſeu Capitularibus, locis aut libris, in quibus annotata reperiuntur, deleri &amp; caſſari, ac Nos de revocatione hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi certiores fecerint, eos non comprehendere, nec eis aliter ſuffragari; quinetiam per hujuſmodi abſolutionem, aut quoſcunque alios actus contrarios tacitos vel expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos, ac etiam per patientiam &amp; tolerantiam noſtram vel Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſorum noſtrorum, quanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> tempore continuatam, praemiſſis omnibus &amp; ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, ac quibuſcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> juribus Sedis Apoſtolicae ac Sanctae <hi>Romanae</hi> Eccleſiae undecun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> &amp; quandocun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> quaeſitis, vel
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61558:19"/> quaerendis nullatenus praeju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicari poſſe aut debere.</p>
                           <p>§ 25. Non obſtantibus pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilegiis, indulgentiis, indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp; literis Apoſtolicis ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralibus vel ſpecialibus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pradictis, vel eorum alicui, ſeu aliquibus aliis cujuſcunque ordinis, ſtatus vel conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, dignitatis &amp; praeeminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae fuerint, etiamſi, ut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, Pontificali, Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ali, Regali, ſeu quavis Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtica &amp; mundana praeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant dignitate, vel eorum Regnis, Provinciis, civitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſeu locis a praedicta Sede ex quavis cauſa etiam per viam contractus aut remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationis, &amp; ſub quavis alia forma &amp; tenore, ac cum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſvis clauſulis, etiam dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatoriarum derogatoriis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſis, etiam continentibus quod excommunicari, ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematizari vel interdici non poſſint, per literas Apoſtolicas non facientes plenam &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſam ac de verbo ad ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum de indulto hujuſmodi, ac de ordinibus, locis, nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus propriis, cognominibus &amp; dignitatibus eorum men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, necnon conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, etiam immemorabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61558:19"/> ac praeſcriptionibus quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumcun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> longiſſimis, &amp; aliis quibuſlibet obſervantiis, ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis vel non ſcriptis, per quae contra hos noſtros Proceſſus ac ſententias, quo minus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludantur in eis, ſe juvare valeant ac tueri. Quae om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quoad hoc, eorum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um tenores, ac ſi ad verbum, nihil penitus omiſſo, inſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur, praeſentibus pro ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſis habentes penitus tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus, &amp; omnino revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: caeteriſque contrariis quibuſcunque.</p>
                           <p>§ 26. Ut vero praeſentes noſtri proceſſus ad publicam omnium notitiam facilius de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducantur, Chartas ſeu Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branas Proceſſus ipſos conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentes, valvis Eccleſiae S. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annis Lateranenſis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae</hi> Principis Apoſtolorum de Urbe appendi faciemus; ut ii, quos Proceſſus hujuſmodi concernunt, quod ad ipſos non pervenerint, aut quod ipſos ignoraverint, nullam poſſint excuſationem praeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere aut ignorantiam allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; cum non ſit veriſimile,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61558:20"/> id remanere incognitum, quod tam patenter omnibus publicatur.</p>
                           <p>§ 27. Inſuper ut Proceſſus ipſi &amp; praeſentes literae, ac omnia &amp; ſingula in eis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenta, eo fiant notiora, quo in pleriſque Civitatibus &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis fuerint publicata; uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſis &amp; ſingulis Patriarchis, Primatibus, Archiepiſcopis, Epiſcopis, &amp; locorum Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariis, &amp; Praelatis ubilibet conſtitutis, per haec ſcripta committimus, &amp; in virtute ſanctae obedientiae diſtricte praecipiendo mandamus; ut per ſe vel per alium ſeu alios praeſentes literas, poſtquam eas receperint, ſeu earum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerint notitiam, ſemel in anno, aut, ſi expedire vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, etiam pluries, in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiis ſuis, dum in eis major populi multitudo ad Divina convenerit, ſolenniter publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, &amp; ad Chriſti fidelium mentes reducant, nuncient, &amp; declarent.</p>
                           <p>§ 28. Caeterum Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chae, Archiepiſcopi, Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi, aliique locorum Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii, &amp; Eccleſiarum Praelati, necnon Rectores, caeterique curam animarum exercentes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61558:20"/> ac Presbytei ſaeculares &amp; quorumvis Ordinum regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ad audiendas peccatorum confeſſiones quavis authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate deputati, tranſumptum praeſentium Literarum penes ſe habeant, eaſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> diligenter legere &amp; percipere ſtudeant.</p>
                           <p>§ 29. Volentes earundum praeſentium tranſumptis, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam impreſſis, Notarii pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lici manu ſubſcriptis, &amp; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillo Judicis Ordinarii Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae Curiae, vel alterius perſonae in dignitate eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtica conſtitutae munitis, eandem prorſus fidem in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio, &amp; extra illud ubique locorum adhibendam fore, quae ipſis praeſentibus adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beretur, ſi eſſent exhibitae vel oſtenſae.</p>
                           <p>§ 30. Nulli ergo omnino hominum liceat hanc pagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam noſtrae excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, anathematizationis, interdicti, innovationis, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodationis, declarationis, proteſtationis, ſublationis, revocationis, commiſſionis, mandati &amp; voluntatis infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, vel ei auſu temerario contraire. Siquis autem hoc attentare praeſumpſerit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignationem Omnipotentis
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61558:21"/> Dei ac Beatorum <hi>Petri</hi> &amp; <hi>Pauli</hi> Apoſtolorum ejus ſe noverit incurſurum.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>Datum <hi>Romae</hi> apud S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum,</hi> 
                                 <date>Anno Incarnationis Dominicae Milleſſimo ſexcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſimo decimo, ſexto Idus <hi>Aprilis,</hi> Pontificatus noſtri anno quinto.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Anno a Nativitate Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Noſtri Jeſu Chriſti milleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſexcenteſimo decimo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, Indict. 11. die vero quarta menſis Aprilis, Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatus Sanctiſſ. in Chriſto Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris &amp; D. N. D. Pauli divina providentia Papae V. anno octavo, ſupradictae literae af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixae &amp; publicatae fuerunt ad Valvas Baſilicarum S. Joannis Lateranenſis &amp; Principis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum, &amp; in acie Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi Florae per nos Baldaſſarem Vacham &amp; Brandimartem Latinum Curſores.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Jacobus Brambilla,</hi> Mag. Curſ.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61558:7"/>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="excerpt_from_papal_bull">
                           <head>The Sixty third Conſtitution of <hi>Paul</hi> V.</head>
                           <p>THe Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tization of all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks whatſoever, and their favourers, and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, or of thoſe who vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Eccleſiaſtical Liberty, or any ways infringe the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this Bull, which is wont to be publiſhed on <hi>Maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day-Thurſday.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>As for almoſt all the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this Bull, (beſides the 3d Extravagant of <hi>Paul II.</hi> and the 5th Extravagant of <hi>Sixtus IV.</hi> in the Title of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Remiſſions) you have them before ordained in the firſt Conſtitution of <hi>Urban. V. fol. 215.</hi> in the 25th Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Julius II. f. 482.</hi> in the 10th Conſtitution of <hi>Paul III. f. 522.</hi> and in the 81ſt Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of <hi>Gregory XIII. f. 348. lib. 2.</hi> Other Bulls of this nature,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61558:8"/> called Bulls <hi>in Caena Domini,</hi> I have purpoſely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, being content with theſe; from which it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that the Popes have made ſome Variation in them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Exigency of the times. Yet I would not omit thoſe which follow, as being eſpecially neceſſary, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly publiſhed upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Chapters of this Bull.</p>
               <p>There is extant therefore in this Collection, a particular Edict of <hi>Nicolas III.</hi> about the 1ſt Section of this Bull in his 2d Conſtitution. <hi>Sup. fol. 143.</hi> concerning <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> there is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, Conſt. 5. of <hi>Pius II. f. 290. l. 1.</hi> concerning §. 4. there is extant, Conſt. 7. of <hi>Pius V. f. 137. l. 2.</hi> concerning §. 7. is extant, Conſt. 3. of <hi>Nicolas V. f. 283. l. 1.</hi> concerning §. 10. is extant a <hi>Canon</hi> of <hi>Calliſtus.</hi> in c. 23. Conſt. 24. qu. 3. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning §. 11. in reſpect of the Cardinals is extant, Conſt. 16. of <hi>Leo X. f. 420. l. 1.</hi> and Conſt. 93. of <hi>Pius V. f. 222. l. 2.</hi> Concerning § 12. is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Conſt. 11. of <hi>Alexander VI. f. 352.</hi> Concerning § 14. is extant Conſt. 2. of <hi>Martin V. f. 239.</hi> and Conſt. 17. of <hi>Innocent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61558:8"/> VIII. f. 343.</hi> and Conſt. 30. of <hi>Leo X. f. 440.</hi> and Conſt. 39. of <hi>Clement VII. f. 505. l. 1.</hi> and Conſt. 19. of <hi>Gregory XIII. f. 290. l. 2.</hi> Concerning § 15. are many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons in the Body of the Law, and Conſt. 10. of <hi>Martin V. f. 247.</hi> Concerning § 19. is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Conſt. 3. of <hi>Urban VI. f. 222.</hi> Concerning § 20. is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Conſt. 8. of <hi>John XXII. f. 174.</hi> and Conſt. 3. of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment VI. f. 212.</hi> and Conſt. 13. of <hi>Leo X. f. 314.</hi> and Conſt. 11. of <hi>Paul IV. f. 595.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another like Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uſually publiſhed on <hi>Maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Thurſday,</hi> is extant in the 62d Conſtitution of our Holy Lord <hi>Urban VIII.</hi> inf. Tom 4.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="papal_bull">
                           <head>Paul Biſhop, Servant of the Servants of God, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual memory of the thing now Decreed.</head>
                           <p>THE Paſtoral vigilance and care of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> being by the duty of his Office continually em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in procuring by all means the peace and tranquility of Chriſtendom, is more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially eminent in retaining and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61558:9"/> preſerving the unity and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of Catholick Faith; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God: That ſo the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Chriſt may not be as Children wavering, nor be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about with every wind of Doctrine, by the cunning craft of men, whereby they lay in wait to deceive; but that all may meet in the unity of the Faith, and the knowledg of the Son of God unto a perfect man: That in the communion and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of this life they may not injure nor offend one another; but rather being joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the bond of Charity, as members of one body under Chriſt the Head, and his Vicar upon Earth the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, from whom the unity of the whole Church doth flow, may be increaſed in edification, and by the aſſiſtance of the Divine Grace may ſo enjoy the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of this preſent life, that they may alſo attain eternal happineſs. For which Reaſons the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, upon this day, which is dedicated to the Anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary commemoration of our Lord's Supper, have been wont
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61558:9"/> ſolemnly to exerciſe the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sword of Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline and wholſom Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of Juſtice by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Supreme Apoſtolate to the glory of God, and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Souls. We therefore, deſiring nothing more than by the guidance of God to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve inviolable the integrity of Faith, publick Peace and Juſtice; following this ancient and ſolemn Cuſtom;</p>
                           <p>§. 1. We excommunicate and anathematize in the name of God Almighty, Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, and by the authority of the Bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and by our own, all Huſſites, Wicle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſts, Lutherans, Zuinglians, Calviniſts, Hugonots, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Trinitarians, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates from the Chriſtian Faith, and all other Hereticks by whatſoever name they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and of whatſoever Sect they be: as alſo their Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Receivers, Favourers, and generally any Defenders of them; together with all who without our Authority, or that of the Apoſtolick See, knowingly read, keep, print, or any ways for any cauſe whatſoever, publickly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61558:10"/> or privately on any pre text or colour defend their Books containing Hereſie, or treating of Religion; as alſo Schiſmaticks, and thoſe who withdraw themſelves, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede obſtinately from the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of us, or the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> for the time being.</p>
                           <p>§ 2. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all and ſingular, of whatſoever ſtation, degree or condition they be; and interdict all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, Colledges and Chapters, by whatſoever name they are called; who appeal from the Orders or Decrees of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, or the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> for the time being to a future General Council; and thoſe by whoſe aid and favour the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal was made.</p>
                           <p>§ 3. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all Pirates, Corſairs and Robbers by Sea, roving about our Sea chiefly from Mount <hi>Argenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere</hi> to <hi>Terracina,</hi> and all their Abetters, Receivers and Defenders.</p>
                           <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61558:10"/>
                           <p>§ 4. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all and ſingular, who when the Ships of any Chriſtians are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther driven out of the way by Tempeſt, or any ways ſuffer ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, convey away any Goods of what kind ſoever, either in the Ships themſelves, or caſt out of the Ships into the Sea, or found on the Shore, as well in our <hi>Tyrrhenian</hi> and <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Seas, as in any other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of Shores of all Seas whatſoever; ſo that they ſhall not be excuſed by any Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Cuſtom, or poſſeſſion of time immemorial, or any other pretext whatſoever.</p>
                           <p>§ 5. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all who impoſe or augment any new Tolls or Gabells in their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, except in caſes permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them by Law, or by eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecial leave of the Apoſtolick See; or, who exact ſuch Taxes forbidden to be impoſed or augmented.</p>
                           <p>§ 6. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all Forgers of Apoſtolick Letters, even in form of a Brief, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61558:11"/> of Supplications reſpecting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence or Juſtice, ſigned by the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by the Vice-chancellours of the Holy see of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by their Deputies, or by the command of the ſaid Pope; as alſo thoſe who falſly publiſh the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Letters, even in form of a Brief; and thoſe who falſly ſign ſuch Supplications in the name of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Vice-chancellour, or their Deputies.</p>
                           <p>§ 7. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all thoſe, who carry or tranſmit to the <hi>Saracens, Turks,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enemies and Foes of the Chriſtian Religion, or to thoſe who are expreſly and by name declared Hereticks by the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of us, or of this Holy See, Horſes, Arms, Iron, duſt of Iron, Tin, Steel, and all kind of Metals, and Warlike Inſtruments, Timber, Hemp, Ropes made as well of Hemp as of any other matter, and that matter whatſoever it be, and other things of this nature, which they make uſe of to the prejudice of Chriſtians and Catholicks: as alſo thoſe who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61558:11"/> by themſelves or others give intelligence of matters relating to the State of Chriſtendom to the <hi>Turks</hi> and Enemies of the Chriſtian Religion to the hurt and prejudice of Chriſtians, or to Hereticks to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Catholick Religion, or who any ways afford to them counſel, aſſiſtance or favour; notwithſtanding any Privileges hitherto granted by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and the aforeſaid See to any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Princes or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths; wherein expreſs mention is not made of this prohibition.</p>
                           <p>§ 8. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all hindering or invading thoſe, who bring Proviſions, or any other things neceſſary, for the uſe of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> as alſo thoſe who forbid, hinder or obſtruct the bringing or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting of them to the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> or who abet the doers of theſe things either by themſelves, or by others; of whatſoever order, preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, condition or quality they be, even although they be Biſhops or Kings, or inveſted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61558:12"/> with any other Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Secular Dignity.</p>
                           <p>§ 9. Farther, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all thoſe who kill, maim, ſpoil, apprehend or detain by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or by others, thoſe who come to the Apoſtolick See, or return from it; as alſo all thoſe who having no ordinary juriſdiction, nor any Delegated by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s or our Judges, raſhly challenging it to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, preſume to commit any like actions againſt thoſe who reſide at the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>§ 10. Farther, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all who kill, maim, wound, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, apprehend, or rob Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers to <hi>Rome,</hi> or Pilgrims for the ſake of Devotion or Pilgrimage going to that City, ſtaying in it, or returning from it; and thoſe who give aid, counſel or favour in theſe caſes.</p>
                           <p>§ 11. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all who ſlay, wound, maim, ſtrike, apprehend, impriſon, detain, or in hoſtile manner purſue the Cardinals of the Holy Church
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61558:12"/> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Patriarchs, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Legats or Nuncios of the Apoſtolick See; or thoſe wo drive them out of their Territories, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, Lands or Dominions; or thoſe who command or allow theſe things to be done, or give aid, counſel and favour to them.</p>
                           <p>§ 12. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all thoſe, who by themſelves or by others ſlay, or any ways ſtrike or deſpoil any Eccleſiaſtical or Secular Perſons having recourſe to the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> for their Cauſes and Affairs, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting and managing them in the ſaid Court, or even the Auditors or Judges deputed for the hearing and managing of the ſaid Cauſes and Affairs, upon occaſion of theſe Cauſes and Affairs: as alſo thoſe who by themſelves or by others di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly preſume to act or procure the ſaid Crimes, or to give aid, counſel or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to them, of whatſoever preheminence or dignity they be.</p>
                           <pb n="12" facs="tcp:61558:13"/>
                           <p>§ 13. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all thoſe, as well Eccleſiaſticks as Seculars, of whatſoever dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity they be, who under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a certain frivolous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from the injuſtice or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture execution of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Letters, even in form of a Brieve, reſpecting as well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as juſtice, as alſo from the injuſtice and future execution of Citations, Inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions, Sequeſtrations, Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, Proceſſes, Executorials and other Decrees, iſſuing out, or which ſhall at any time iſſue out from <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid See, or our Legates, Nuncios, or Preſidents, from the Auditors of our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Palace and Apoſtolick Chamber, from our Commiſſaries, and other Apoſtolick Judges and Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates: as alſo thoſe, who any other ways have recourſe to Secular Courts and the Lay Power; and who cauſe ſuch Appeals to be admitted by the Secular Courts, even although the Procurator and Advocate of the Exchequer ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it; or who cauſe the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                              <pb n="13" facs="tcp:61558:13"/> aforeſaid Letters, Citations, Inhibitions, Sequeſtrations, Monitories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be ſeized or retained; or thoſe who hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or forbid the ſaid Letters to be put in execution, either ſimply, or without their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, conſent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or examination; or who hinder or forbid Scrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners or Notaries from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king or delivering when made to the Parties concerned any Inſtruments or Acts concerning the execution of theſe Letters and Proceſſes; or who appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, ſtrike, wound, impriſon, detain, drive out of Cities, Places and Kingdoms, deſpoil of their Goods, terrify, vex and threaten, either by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or by others, publickly or privately, the Parties, or their Agents, Kindred on both ſides, their Friends, Notaries, the Executors or Sub-execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the ſaid Letters, Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Monitories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or who any other way preſume directly or indirectly to forbid, ordain and command, any Perſons in general <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> in particular, to betake themſelves, or haue recourſe to the See of <hi>Rome</hi> to proſecute their Affairs of any kind, or to obtain Indulgences
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61558:14"/> or Letters, or who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them to obtain the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, or to make uſe of them when obtained of the ſaid See; or who preſume to retain the ſaid Indulgences in their own hands, or in the hands of a Notary or a Scrivener, or any other way.</p>
                           <p>§ 14. Further we Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and Anathematize all and ſingular, who by themſelves or by others, by their own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and <hi>de facto,</hi> under pretence of any exemptions, or any other Apoſtolick Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Letters, take away the cognizance of Benefices, and Tithes, and other ſpiritual Cauſes, or annexed to ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als from our Auditors and Commiſſaries, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Judges; and hinder the proceeding and audience of them, and the Perſons, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Convents, Colledges, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to proſecute the ſaid Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; or who intrude themſelves as Judges in the Cognizance of them; or who by order, or any other way compel the Plaintiffs to withdraw, or cauſe to be withdrawn, their Citations, or Inhibitions, or any other Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters decreed in the ſpiritual
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61558:14"/> Court; and the Defendants, againſt whom ſuch Inhibitions were iſſued out, to procure, or conſent to be abſolved from the Cenſures or Puniſhments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them; or who any ways hinder the execution of Apoſtolick Letters, Executori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, Proceſſes and Decrees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; or give their allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, counſel, or aſſent to it, even under pretence of hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing violence, or any other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts whatſoever, or even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they ſhall Petition us, or cauſe us to be Petitioned for our better information, as is commonly pretended, unleſs they proſecute ſuch Petitions before us and the Apoſtolick See in lawful form; even although thoſe who commit ſuch things ſhould be Preſidents of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, Councils, or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Chancellors, Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chancellors, ordinary or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Counſellors of any ſecular Princes, (whether they be Emperors, Kings, Dukes, or any other dignity) or Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendataries or Vicars.</p>
                           <pb n="16" facs="tcp:61558:15"/>
                           <p>§. 15. Alſo thoſe who under pretence of their Office, or at the inſtance of any party, or of any others, draw, or cauſe and procure to be drawn, directly, or indirectly, upon any pretext whatſoever, Eccleſiaſtical Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Chapters, Convents, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of any Churches, before them to their Tribunal, Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Chancery, Counſel, or Parliament, againſt the Rules of the Canon-Law; as alſo thoſe who for any cauſe, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any pretext, or by pretence of any Cuſtom or Priviledg, or any other way, ſhall make, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act, and publiſh any Statutes, Orders, Conſtitutions, Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, or any other Decrees in general or in particular; or ſhall uſe them when made and enacted; whereby the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Liberty is violated, or any ways injured or depreſſed, or by any other means reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; or whereby the Rights of us and of the ſaid See, and of any other Churches, are any way directly or indirectly, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely or expreſly prejudged.</p>
                           <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61558:15"/>
                           <p>§ 16. Alſo thoſe who upon this account directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly hinder Archbiſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and other ſuperior and inferior Prelates, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordinary Eccleſiaſtical Judges whatſoever by any means, either by impriſoning or moleſting their Agents, Proctors, Domeſticks, kindred on both ſides, or by any other way, from exerting their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical juriſdiction againſt any perſons whatſoever, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Canons and ſacred Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions and Decrees of General Councils, and eſpecially that of <hi>Trent,</hi> do appoint; as alſo thoſe who after the ſentence and decrees of the Ordinaries themſelves, or of thoſe delegated by them, or by any other means eluding the judgment of the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Court, have recourſe to Chanceries or other ſecular Courts, and procure thence Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions and even Penal Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates to be decreed againſt the ſaid Ordinaries and Delegates and executed againſt them; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thoſe who make and execute theſe Decrees, or who give aid, counſel, countenance or favour to them.</p>
                           <pb n="18" facs="tcp:61558:16"/>
                           <p>§ 17. Alſo thoſe who uſurp any Juriſdictions, Fruits, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues and Emoluments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and the Apoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick See, and any Eccleſiaſtical perſons upon account of any Churches, Monaſteries, or other Eccleſiaſtical benefices; or who upon any occaſion or cauſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſter the ſaid Revenues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the expreſs leave of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> or others having lawful power to do it.</p>
                           <p>§ 18. Alſo thoſe who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the like ſpecial and expreſs licence of the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> impoſe Tributes, Tenths, Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, Subſidies, and other Charges upon Clergy-men, Prelates, and other Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal perſons, and the Goods, Fruits, Revenues and Emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of them and of the Churches, Monaſteries, and other Eccleſiaſtical Benefices; and exact them by divers ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices, or even receive them ſo impoſed from the Clergy, although they ſhould of their own accord grant and give them: Alſo thoſe who by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or others directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly fear not to do, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute or procure the ſaid things,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61558:16"/> or to give aid, counſel or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to them, of whatſoever preheminence, dignity, order, condition or quality they be, although they be Emperors, or Kings, or Princes, Dukes, Earls, Barons, and other Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates whatſoever, even Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of Kingdoms, Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Cities and Territories, Counſellors, and Senators, or inveſted even with any Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical Dignity. Renewing the Decrees ſet forth concerning theſe Matters by the Sacred Canons, as well in the laſt Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> as in other General Councils, together with the Cenſures and Puniſhments contained in them.</p>
                           <p>§ 19. Further, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all and every Magiſtrates and Judges, Notaries, Scribes, Executors, Subexecutors, any ways intruding themſelves in capital or criminal cauſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Eccleſiaſtical Perſons by proceſſing, baniſhing, or appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending them, or pronouncing or executing any ſentences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, without the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, particular and expreſs licence of this Holy Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal See; alſo thoſe who extend
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61558:17"/> ſuch licences to Perſons or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not expreſſed, or any other way injuſtly abuſe them; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Offenders ſhould be Counſellors, Senators, Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Chancellours, Vice-chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, or entitled by any other name.</p>
                           <p>§ 20. Farther, We excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and anathematize all thoſe, who by themſelves, or by others, directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, under any title or colour whatſoever ſhall preſume to invade, deſtroy, ſeize and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, in whole or in part, the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>Sicily,</hi> the Iſlands of <hi>Sardinia</hi> and <hi>Corſica,</hi> the Territories about <hi>Faro,</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Spoleto,</hi> the County of <hi>Venoſo,</hi> and <hi>Sabinum, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca di Ancona, Maſſa, Treba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Romandiola, Campania,</hi> and the Maritime Provinces, and their Territories and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the Lands held in ſpecial commiſſion by the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulfi,</hi> and our Cities of <hi>Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Caeſena, Ariminum, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neventum, Citta di Caſtello, Todi, Ferrara, Comaclo,</hi> and other Cities, Lands and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Rights belonging to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61558:17"/> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted mediately or immediately to the ſaid Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> alſo thoſe who preſume by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers means to uſurp, diſturb, detain, and vex the ſupreme Juriſdiction of the ſaid Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions belonging to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> alſo their Adherents, Favourers and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, or thoſe who any way give aſſiſtance, counſel or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to them.</p>
                           <p>§ 21. Willing that our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Proceſſes, and all and every thing contained in theſe Letters, continue in force, and be put in excution; till other Proceſſes of this kind be made and publiſhed by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> for the time being.</p>
                           <p>§ 22. In fine, none may be abſolved from the aforeſaid Cenſures by any other than by the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> unleſs he be at the point of death, nor even then, unleſs he giveth caution to ſtand to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Church, and give ſatisfaction. In all other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes none ſhall be abſolved, not even under pretence of any Faculties or Indulgences grant<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61558:18"/> and renewed by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and the ſaid See, and the Decrees of any Council, by Words, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or any other Writing, in general or in particular, to any Perſons Eccleſiaſtical, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and Regular of any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, even of the Mendicant and Military Orders, or to any Perſons inveſted with Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, or any greater Dignity, and to Orders themſelves and their Monaſteries, Convents, Houſes and Chapters, to Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Confraternities, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, Hoſpitals, and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Places, as alſo to Laymen, although they ſhould be Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, or eminent in any other ſecular Dignity.</p>
                           <p>§ 23. If by chance any ſhall againſt the tenor of theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, <hi>de facto,</hi> preſume to beſtow the benefit of Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon any ſuch involved in excommunication and ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema, or any of them; we include them in the ſentence of Excommunication, and ſhall afterwards proceed more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely againſt them both by ſpiritual and temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as we ſhall think moſt convenient.</p>
                           <pb n="23" facs="tcp:61558:18"/>
                           <p>§ 24. Declaring and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting that no Abſolution, altho ſolemnly made by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, or any other way avail the aforeſaid excommunicated Perſons comprehended under theſe preſent Letters; unleſs they deſiſt from the premiſſes with a firm purpoſe, of never committing the like thing; nor thoſe, who, as was before ſaid, have made Statutes againſt the Eccleſiaſtical Liberty; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they firſt publickly revoke theſe Statutes, Orders, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, Pragmaticks and Decrees, and cauſe them to be blotted and expunged out of the Archives, Rolls, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters wherein they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and farther certify <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s of this revocation: moreover, that by any ſuch Abſolution, or any other contrary Acts, tacit or expreſs, or even by the connivance and toleration of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and our Succeſſours for how long time ſoever continued, none nor any of the Premiſſes, nor any Right of the Apoſtolick See and Holy Church of <hi>Rome</hi> howſoever and whenſoever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, or to be obtained, can or ought to be prejudged or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any prejudice.</p>
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61558:19"/>
                           <p>§ 25. Notwithſtanding any Priviledges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Indulgences, Grants, and Apoſtolick Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters general er ſpecial, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Holy See to any of the aforeſaid Perſons, or any one of them, or any others, of whatſoever order, quality or condition, dignity and prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence they be; although, as was before ſaid, they ſhould be Biſhops, Emperours, Kings, or eminent in any other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick or Secular Dignity, or to their Kingdoms, Provinces, Cities, and Dominions, for any cauſe whatſoever, even by way of contract or reward, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any other form and tenor, and with any Clauſes whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, even derogatory of thoſe which ſhould derogate from them; or even containing that the ſaid Perſons or Places ſhall not be excommunicated, ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematized or interdicted by any Apoſtolick Letters, which do not make full and expreſs mention and exact repetition of the ſaid Grant, and of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Places, Proper names, Sirnames and Dignities of the ſaid Perſons; as alſo notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61558:19"/> all Cuſtoms, even im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorial, and Preſcriptions, how long ſoever, and any other Obſervances written or not written, by which the ſaid Perſons may help and defend themſelves againſt theſe our Proceſſes and Cenſures from being included in them. All which Grants, as far as relates to this matter, and the whole tenor of them, accounting them expreſſed in theſe Preſents as if they had been verbatim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, nothing omitted, we utterly aboliſh and wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke; and notwithſtanding any other Pleas which may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to the contrary.</p>
                           <p>§ 26. But that theſe our preſent Proceſſes may more eaſily come to the knowledge of all Perſons; We have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Papers and Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments containing the Proceſſes themſelves to be affixed in the City to the doors of the Church of St. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and of the Church of the Prince of the Apoſtles; that thoſe whom theſe Proceſſes concern, may pretend no excuſe or alledge ignorance, as if they had not come to their knowledge; ſince it is not probable, that ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61558:20"/> remain unknown, which is ſo openly publiſhed to all men.</p>
                           <p>§ 27. Moreover, that the Proceſſes themſelves, and theſe preſent Letters, and all and every thing contained in them may become more manifeſt by being publiſhed in many Cities and Places; We by theſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings entruſt, and in vertue of holy obedience ſtrictly charge and command all and ſingular Patriarchs, Primates, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Ordinaries of Places, and Prelates whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſtituted, that by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or ſome other or others, after they ſhall have received theſe preſent Letters, or have knowledge of them, they ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly publiſh them in their Churches once a year or oftner, if they ſee convenient, when the greater part of the People ſhall be met for celebration of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service; put faithful Chriſtians in mind of them, relate them, and declare them.</p>
                           <p>§ 28. Laſtly, all Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and other Ordinaries of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Prelates of Churches, as alſo all Rectors, and others having cure of Souls, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61558:20"/> Prieſts ſecular and regular of whatſoever Orders, deputed by any authority to hear confeſſion of ſins, ſhall have a Tranſcript of theſe preſent Letters by them, and ſhall diligently ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to read and underſtand them.</p>
                           <p>§ 29. Our farther pleaſure is, that the ſame credit in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and out of judgment, ſhall in all places be given to Copies, although Printed, of theſe preſents, ſubſcribed by any publick Notary, and ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ordinary Judge of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other perſon in Eccleſiaſtical dignity; as would be given to theſe preſents themſelves, if they ſhould be produced or ſhewn.</p>
                           <p>§ 30. Let no man therefore infringe, or boldly and raſhly oppoſe this our Letter of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, Anathematiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Interdict, Innovation, Innodation, Declaration, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, Abolition, Revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Commiſſion, Command and Pleaſure: But if any one ſhall preſume to attempt it; let him know that he ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the diſpleaſure of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and of his Bleſſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61558:21"/> Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>Given at <hi>Rome</hi> from St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
                                 <date>in the year of our Lord's Incarnation, One thouſand ſix hundred and ten, the eighth of <hi>April,</hi> in the fifth year of our Popedom.</date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>In the year, from the birth of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt 1613. Indict. 11. the 4th day of the Month <hi>April,</hi> and the eighth year of the Popedom of our moſt Holy Father in Chriſt, and our Lord <hi>Paul V.</hi> by Divine Providence Pope, the aforeſaid Letters were affixed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed at the Doors of the Churches of St. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> and the Prince of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and in the field of <hi>Flora,</hi> by us <hi>Balthazar Vacha</hi> and <hi>Brandimars Latini</hi> Curſors.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>James Brambilla,</hi> Mag. Curſ.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61558:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
